um hey Rob I hope you're doing well I am
a fresh graduate in a foreign country
and I find it very hard to get a job and
not have residency just mostly negate
most chances to have a job I am thinking
on going my
way uh going my own way entrepreneurial
way and I would love your idea on that
thank you okay and then there's the name
um so this is a very valid question I as
you know I speak French and Russian I
have a a a large uh percentage of people
from the International Community from
England and other places and all over
really in my professional Learning
Network uh which we'll talk about in a
separate video about how to form your
own professional Learning Network and
this is a really common question that I
have gotten over the years since I've
started streaming so since
2020 and the answer is I don't know and
and I know that that's a lot a big
mouthful for me to waste your time but
I've had I've had people tell me that
they've done everything from the Boost
and they've tried everything and they
still can't get a job in America and
they're trying to work elsewhere so I'm
going to brainstorm a couple of things
that I think might help the
International Community but I want to
start by answering you very clearly I
have no idea um my experience is 100%
limited to working in America in terms
of it now of course people know I was a
Russian Cruise director uh and travel
guide I've been to the Caribbean I was a
much Mormon missionary I've
internationally I've traveled quite a
bit actually took um an entire tour I
was sent to to Nago Japan to cover the
Olympics for Nike I I've been around the
block internationally but I've never
worked
internationally and in terms of me going
to work outside of America I will
confess I want to learn teach English as
a second language uh as a method of
doing that but I probably would teach
coding instead now um just to you know
pay my way while I travel the globe and
stay tuned I might actually do that one
of my dreams is to actually truly you
know do a a safe bik tour um IRL like
many IRL twitch streamers do but back to
the topic so how do you get a job in
America if you don't live here the
answer is it's hard and and frankly I
think you should probably not try I if I
know that sounds really bad to say but I
think that your best bet is to work for
a Contracting firm but I have no basis
for saying that my feeling is that if
you work for an international
Contracting firm and this is
particularly for people in India um I
don't mind saying let me share a couple
stories so one of them was while was at
IBM there was about 25 on our team and
it got Whitted down to three and all the
other people were hired from
Brazil uh and Brazil India and Romania
and so America hired from those
organizations now at IBM it's a
multinational so they were just able to
hire from you know that department in
those countries um and IBM by the way
also their entire software division is
in all plac of all places they could
have it it's in Toronto Canada and the
reason for that in my opinion and I I
don't have any um you know proof of this
but the reason I think that IBM IBM's
been around the block a lot they they
have figured out a bunch of things and
they've survived some of the biggest
deficits ever in terms of profit and
everything so they may have a lot of
other problems but one thing that they
really know how to do is to stay in
business and to get good people I mean
they immediately lose those good people
um but and one of the things that they
did is they they I believe they hire
people in Toronto because they can get
Internationals easier
um and I I have no basis for saying that
this is just a hunch but my hunch is I
mean if you go to Toronto Canada and you
see the it there's like it's it's it's
insane like every major Silicon Valley
company and every other company huge
Banks and huge insurance agencies huge
Contracting firms they all have there's
this massive it pre presence presence in
Toronto Canada um people from Toronto
including dimma if you're out there wave
and people that I know uh um you know
Dennis last miles um they are in they're
in Toronto and they'll tell you that
there's this like influx of money and
and stuff so much so that it's really
straight jacking real estate up and the
point is is that Toronto is a real real
hotbed for particularly software
engineering and technologists H and I
believe the reason for that is because
they are it's easier to move to Canada
and to work for one of these American
companies or these these these
multinationals that's based in America
and uh and yeah and so they they go
there and they they get the job and then
you know depending on on on visas and
stuff they they come to America now to
be fair if you look at who's running the
companies in America including some of
the biggest their you know expats from
other foreign countries have been
running the show in America for many of
the biggest companies and I'm not going
to delineate them all just go look at
the upper echelons of most of the big it
companies in Silicon Valley right now
they are not American Born people and
for better or worse and I I that is not
a commentary on multiculturalism that is
just a fact and so apparently it's
possible for you to get here and to work
here and I know that some of them go
back in fact one story from my personal
life uh an international uh systems
administrator that I worked with uh from
India Indian national great guy elas was
his name um and I worked with him as a
system administrator um and he was an NT
systems administrator and he was
supporting his entire family sending
money back uh while he lived in in in
Oregon actually in Vancouver and uh
across the the river there over in
Vancouver Washington and he and I um you
know we we work together a lot and at
fact he's the first one who introduced
me to Indian a lot of you know single
guy Indian food including mango pickle
uh I still have kind of a fond memory of
him uh having me come over to his
apartment once and and introducing me to
all these fun things and he was just
smiling like crazy because I was like oh
my God this is so good and and you know
just stuff I've never even heard of
before it was really it was really a fun
time I really miss elas actually um but
I remember him telling me about his his
his own International jour
and what he was doing and somehow he got
a job for IBM in the Contracting area of
IBM internet Global Services and I don't
know how but he was able to move to
America probably on a work visa I'm
guessing and he came by himself uh
probably because he didn't want to have
to deal with all the Visas and expense
of having his whole family here and and
he would work for a large percentage of
the year and he would send back his
money and I remember him very
specifically telling me he was
supporting his entire extended family
off of the income that he was making as
a systems administrator an N systems
administrator on my team um and after
the account went away that I was in he
he actually went over to work uh for a
different account he was on a uh I think
it was a it was it was a gym equipment
account I can't remember the name of it
but you know and we we we kept
connections on LinkedIn which I'll do a
separate video about for a very long
time um and you know I've contact with
him but I just remember that he now I've
never actually asked any of these people
I do have one other story of an
international another person from India
um that I that I work with currently um
and I got to be really careful please do
not dox where I work if you know and
please also do not dox this individual
but they also came from India they were
also working here um they were also
working for a Contracting firm and they
had decided to move to America um and I
believe they actually had uh American
citizenship I did not know that yet but
same same sort of situation they're
sending back a ton of money to India uh
supporting the family there uh this
particular case which if you're an
international I really want to emphasize
this particular part of the story this
person um went back uh I think it was
Christmas and there was a there was a
snafu with their Visa with their work
visa and they ended up being
stranded uh back in India for two months
unable to work and and it was horrible
it was horrible it was all it wasn't
that person's fault at all it was all
based on uh this crazy stupid things um
that happened between um you know there
were a couple people that that did it um
and that that were involved I I don't
even know all the details all I know is
this poor person this poor amazing
kubernetes engineer was stuck you know
stuck with their family and unable to
make a dime uh for up to two two
something months and they eventually got
it all worked out and they were able to
come back over here so actually answered
uh another one of my things oh hey we
have Anonymous gifter like ruining my
YouTube videos love you thank you for
the money um so so that was somebody who
came over and uh was was over here on a
Visa and actually went back and then
something happened with the VISA and
they weren't able to come back so so
apparently it is true that you can get
it Visa um I think I think at the at the
end of this video haven't gone through
these stories um that and another thing
too I helped um some Russians seeking uh
asylum in America I helped them write an
affidavit uh in English to be able to do
that um and that I think I think that
that helped um as long they they were
seeking po that was always really tough
for me because they were they were
making assertions about their situation
in Russia that I could not validate but
they needed me to to help um them write
the English and so I wrote the English
with the affidavit um and and help them
move here um so that that's the extent
of my experience on it I think I think
if I were going to do this I if I were
International and depending on the
country it I mean it really really
depends on the country I I mean there's
an an ungodly amount of it work and I
know for a fact in Italy and Romania and
France and England and Brazil and India
of course uh and I uh um uh what was I
going to say no Pakistan Pakistan has
some as well not as much as India but um
and of course in Asia I I would I would
look for work there now I know that it's
probably a lot harder for you to find
work there if you have the opportunity
though to come to America on a work visa
temporarily so I think I think the
conclusion here is that people should
look
for um they should look for
multinational companies that have
offices in their country and try to to
figure it out now I understand in India
I I do not know this but I understand
from hearing other people talk about
this that working in it in India is
extremely competitive apparently it's ex
it's really Cutthroat um if you have any
personal experience with that I'd love
to hear in the comments um I don't know
that there's no way I could know that
but um I will say this I cannot compete
on the open market against people in the
International Community because I am I
have to live on an I have to pay for
American prices for everything I
actually tried to do that there was one
of these um sites where you could like
you know like gig kind of sites and you
would do a thing uh and you would get
out you would out bid somebody else and
you would you know do whatever the
coding was for them and I would never
win because I could I mean people people
from other countries were bidding like
$4 for like a 40-hour project and I was
like there's no way I can compete there
um so that's possibly uh one way to get
some work um if you are international
and your cost of living is considerably
less than America the single best
Advantage you have is you are a cheaper
resource than everybody else now you may
have your heart set on coming to America
and making American money but if you
don't you you can definitely beat the
Americans in terms of cost because you
are not required to pay as much now
another there's kind of another message
there and that message is to the
Americans um if you want to double your
income move to a country work for a
multinational and move to a country
where the cost of living is half uh and
people are doing this in fact I did this
uh I was in I was in Tucson and I was
paying a lot of money for for a lot more
um and our insurance went up and
everything and I same exact job and I
moved to North Carolina and I
effectively you know increased my income
by about I would say 10 or 15% because I
was now in an area uh where that's true
I've heard of people moving from Silicon
Valley to Montana uh I've heard of
people moving all over the country right
so one of the best tricks you can do
here is get hired by uh a company making
a wage that's set by that location
because you have older compan that have
not figured out how to properly adjust
the income based on you know remote work
and stuff and so they're still paying
like a New York salary even though you
live in Idaho you know or something I
got nothing bad I love Idaho so you know
the point being is that you can actually
make a lot of money uh by working in an
area where your cost of living is a lot
less and if you're an international
person you can leverage that Advantage
um by getting work I mean the same thing
that Americans complain about about all
of the Outsourcing that's going overseas
because it's cheaper and I mean I hate
to say it that's just the way of the
world that's just how it is until all
the incomes come up that's going to be
the way it's going to be for a long time
and the bottom line in most American
most American corporate you know boards
is we just want to reduce our our costs
and they're going to continue to
Outsource work um to other places
there's a futurist who talks about uh
the return of of of a lot of
manufacturing jobs to America based on
robotics um which is going to be
interesting to watch so if you're in
that robotics field um that there the
prediction from that particular futurist
is that that we're the America is going
to see a lot of manufacturing jobs
return once robotics starts to take over
uh a little bit more over here we'll
start to see that and that that's
interesting if you're an American um
people don't like America
internationally for lots of reasons I
don't want to get into politically but
so um and honestly right now there's
sort of this insular nationalistic um
ideology that's permeating all of the
world and and it does not like um the
idea of jobs going overseas so if you
are an international and you are seeking
employment in America um just know that
about that be sensitive to that because
if you there let me tell you a true
story from a senior executive at
Microsoft which I shall not name uh came
you know work be kind of situation came
to came here worked at micros oft built
up the company built millions and
millions of dollars got lots of senior
architectural experience and then he's
now leading the Chinese government's
division building up uh tenzen and and
all of those amazing areas inside of
China so this is a person who came to
America I'm not suggesting there Aspire
an intelligence agent or an asset in any
way although it's very likely um and
they they came here and they got tons of
experience experience they got all the
knowhow about how to run a company about
the internal network of Microsoft and
right now they are leading the charge
building up the shenzen area of China
which is kicking butt entire American
institutions are moving their
headquarters to shenzen and you know
politics is somebody's going to write
bad things in the comments I can't help
it but I'm just stating the facts of the
situation so if if you are international
and you want to work in America or you
want to be employed by America Americans
I'm not saying that we're going to hate
you for trying to come here and work and
go back but you just need to be
sensitive to that because there is a lot
of strong emotion in America right now
uh with regard to International people
taking stealing our jobs I don't agree
with that at all because a lot of those
people who say those things don't lift a
finger to even watch a free video that
some random person put on the internet
to help them get a better Tech
job but they'll complain about losing
their job okay I should probably stop
now so you know and and there's one
thing about the International Community
I'm I'm just going to say it they seem
to me from where I'm sitting they seem
very very motivated to put in the hours
and to do the work to learn the skills
necessary to get the tech jobs and I
don't know if that's because there's a
greater promise for wealth by making
American dollars while living in a place
that they they have a lower cost of I
don't know the reason I just know that
from where I'm sitting my impression is
that I meet on a daily basis I and I
stream too but the I mean just the
number of Americans who attend the
beginner boost compared to the number of
people internationally who are in the
beginner boost my feeling is it's not
even 50/50 and then I have to ask myself
where's all the Americans and I'm not
slamming on Americans I love Americans
but they just they they just don't show
up I don't know what's going on with
that I I want to change that I don't I
don't I don't know what's going on so so
if you're International just know about
the Pol political climate and the answer
is maybe go to
Toronto and work for multinational
consider working in your own country
first and and then also consider uh
coming here on a work visa and then
figuring out some way um to Parlay that
work visa into something more and many
many many people have done that uh lots
of people that I work for uh when I was
at Nike I want to say probably I at
least half of my team were Indian
Nationals and um they were wonderful
awesome people they were really
dedicated they're super intelligent a
lot of fun to work with so were their
Americans on my team they were great so
so um I I suppose one of the takeaways
of this is if you're going to work in it
just know it fundamentally is
Multicultural there are people from all
over the globe who who get into it and
it is kind of fun to jokingly you know
in a cliche way characterize certain
countries um by the way one of my
favorite teams to ever work for was the
Italians I had so much fun on that team
because they were they just kept us we
were just laughing the whole time we got
a lot of stuff done but we were also
doing a lot of laughing and that's not
always true for all the other cultures
I'm going to tell you that right now um
so anyway uh if you're International
give it a shot hopefully that helps
please don't yell at me in the comments
I don't mean anything bad here I'm just
sharing my experience